A difirencia de la conferencia pasada, no tengo premios para dar.
Solo te voy a decir como vivir tu vida.
Esta charla es en realidad sobre una forma de vivir tu vida que la mayoria de la gente no conoce.
A medida que te acerques a tu carrera, vas a escuchar un monton acerca de como "seguir tu pasion",
o "hacer algo que amas".
Voy a hablarles sobre algo un poco diferente.
Voy a hablar sobre seguir un principio,
encontrar un principio guia para tu trabajo, algo que creas que es importante
necesario y correcto, y lo uses para guiar lo que haces.
Hay tres partes en esta conferencia.
Primero voy a hablar sobre el principio que guia mucho de mi trabajo,
y tratar de que echen un vistazo de lo que se obtiene de eso.
Y, voy a hablar sobre otras personas que han vivido su vida de éste modo.
cuales son sus principios, en que creen.
Pero esos son todos ejemplo, para ayudar a pensar en que crees tu,
y como quieres vivir tu vida.
Para empezar conmigo: Las ideas son muy importantes.
Yo pienso que traer ideas al mundo es una de las cosas mas importantes que la gente hace.
Y también pienso que las grandes ideas, en forma de arte genial, historias, invenciones, teorias cientificas,
esas toman vida propia,
que da sentido a nuestas vidas como personas.
Yo pienso mucho acerca de como las personas crean ideas, y en como las ideas crecen.
Y en particular, que conjunto de herramientas crean un ambiente saludable para que las ideas crezcan.
Ahora, he pasado mucho de mi tiempo a traves de los años haciendo herramientas creativas, usandolas,
pensando mucho sobre ellas, y aqui esta algo que he llegado a creer:
Los inventores necesitan una coneccion inmediata con lo que estan creando.
Ese es mi prinicipio.
Los inventores necesitan una coneccion con lo que crean.
Lo que trato de decir con esto es que cuando estas haciendo algo, si haces un cambio,
o tomas una desciscion, tu nescesitas ver un efecto inmediato sobre eso.
No puede haber una demora, no puede haber nada oculto.
Los inventores tiene que ser capaces de ver lo que estan haciendo
Ahora voy a mostrarles una serie de casos donde note que este principio es violado
Y también voy a mostrarles que hice al respecto.
Y luego voy a hablarles de un contexto mayor, en donde esto funciona
Para empezar, pensemos acerca de programar.
Asi es como la programación funciona : escribes un monton de codigo en un editor de texto,
tratas de imaginar en tu cabeza que hara cada linea de codigo.
Y luego los complias y ejecutas, y algo sucede.
En este caso, esto es solo JavaScript, Canvas, y dibuja este pequeño árbol.
Pero, si hay algo mal en la escena,
o si voy y hago cambios, o si tengo mas ideas
Tengo que ir devuelta al código,
y editar, compilarlo y ejecutarlo,
Mirar como luce.
Si algo va mal, vas devuelta al código.
La mayoría de mi tiempo lo paso en el código, trabajando a ciegas en un editor de texto,
sin una conexión inmediata a lo que hago,
que es lo que tratare de hacer.
Siento que esto va encontra del principio que tengo,
que un inventor necesita una conexión inmediata con lo que esta creando,
he probado un entorno de programacion que va a ser mucho mas acorde a mi principio.
Lo que tengo aquí es una foto en un lado y el código en el otro,
y esta parte dibuja el cielo y esta parte las montañas.
esto dibuja un arbol,
y cuando hago cualquier cambio al código
el dibujo cambia inmediatamente.
El código y el dibujo estan siempre sincronizados, no hay un compliar y ejecutar.
Yo solo cambio cosas en el código
y veo el cambio en el código.
Y ahora que tenemos esta conexión inmediata entre
el código y el dibujo,
podemos pensar maneras de cambiar el código fuera de tipear...
Por ejemplo, este numero es la cantidad de ramas
Si quisiera controlar ese numero, solo tengo que apuntar mi puntero a él,
presionar mi tecla ctrl, y subir y bajar el valor del numero.
Yo puedo ver como luce muchas ramas o pocas ramas
y puedo llenar con lo que me parece artisticamente correcto.
Y funciona para cualquier numero en el código
Solo apunto a él y lo subo y bajo
Y algunos de estos numeros aquí, se lo que hacen
Pero aun es algo sorprendete verlos hacerlo [risas]
Y otras acciones son completamente sorprendentes
[risas]
Estoy aquí, tengo este
bucle donde estoy contando hasta dicesiceis,
Estoy poniendo dieciseis pequeñas flores rosas en cada rama.
Y puedo bajar el numero para menos flores o subirlo para más.
Pero, miren a lo que estoy haciendo aquí:
**Solo estoy moviendo ese número hacia arriba y abajo alrededor de veinto o parecido:
y tiene un efecto reluciente muy interesante;
parece como que el viento esta soplando entre los arboles.
Y la primera vez que vi esto inmediatamente me puse a pensar sobre ello
como podría usar este efecto para una animación.
Cómo podría haber descubierto eso si hubiese tenido que compilar y ejecutar entre cada cambio?
Mucho del arte, mucho de la invencion es descubrimiento,
y no puedes descubrir nada si no logras ver lo que estas haciendo.
Les he mostrado que sucede modificando el código, vamos a agregar algo de código.
Me gustaría poner un sol aquí en el cielo,
Ire a la función dibujarCielo,
y quiero rellenar en un círculo,
empiezo a escribir contexto.llenarCirculo,
y apenas que empiezo a escribir, recibo la lista de autcompletado
de los diferentes metodos de llenado.
Estos son las cosas que puedo tipear aqui: llenarCirculo, llenarRectangulo, llenarTexto.
y cuando me muevo para arriba o para abajo en esta lista de autocompletado,
Inmediatamente veo que hace cada una de ellas.
Yo no tengo que imaginar que hara a partir del nombre del metodo.
No tengo que mirar la documentación,
Yo lo veo, inmediatamente.
Yo quiero un círculo,
y solo voy a ajustar la coordenada X
y la coordenada Y,
cambiar el radio un poco...
And that looks about right.
***y mirar
Probablemente debería ser amarillo,
así que voy a definir el estilo de pintado
Context.fillStyle, el mismo autocompletado como antes antes,
elijo el estilo
me ofrece color "blanco" por omisión,
y puedo cambiar ese código de color de la misma forma que cambio cualquier número,
Puso la tecla control, y obtendo una paleta de colores.
Así que elijo a lindo color amarillo para mi sol.
Aunque... el blanco tiene algo interesante, pienso...
Algo que no esperaba, pero,
con el blanco, se parece mas a una luna, cierto ?
Hey, se ve que ahora es de noche...
Tener una conexión inmediata permite a las ideas salir a la superficie
y desarrollar en formas que antes eran imposibles.
Pero, pienso que aún existe un problema aquí.
Es este: tengo este dibujo,
tengo este código al lado,
y tengo que manetener un mapa en mi cabeza que los relaciona a los dos.
Así que tengo todas estas lineas de código,
y si miro esta linea, no puede ver inmediatamente que hace.
Así que esto es lo que puedo hacer:
Puedo mantener pulsada la tecla Option,
mi cursor se convierte en una lupa,
y ahora cuando de deplazo sobre cada linea de código,
aparece resaltado el dibujo
eso es lo que está siendo dibujado por esa linea.
Entonces, si quiero conocer qué está haciendo esta funciíon,
Solo exploro dentro de la función y veo qué aparece resaltado.
Aquí tengo dos llamadas a drawMountain; no se cual es cual;
bueno, esta es esa montaña, y esta es esa otra montaña.
Y esto funcionaría de la otra forma también;
si veo una parte del dibujo,
Necesito conocer que código fué el responsable de dibujarlo.
Así que hago lo mismo, mantengo pulsada la tecla Option,
y mientras me muevo sobre cada pixel del dibujo,
como ven a la derecha
salta a la linea de código que dibujó ese pixel.
Así esto dibujo el cielo, y esto dibujó el árbol
Esto dibujo las hojas
Es realmente importante hacer esta vinculación
Pero también es realmente útil navegar alrededor
Así, quiero hacer que el sol sea un poco mas grande.
Salto ahí, lo hago un poco mas grande
Quiero hacer crecer un poquito el árbol,
así que salto ahí, y hago crecer el árbol un poco.
Quiero agrandar las montañas un poco.
Voy ahí, agrando las montañas un poco
Y puedo hacer estos cambios tan rápidos como se me van ocurriendo
Y es tan importante para el proceso creativo -
ser capaz de intentar ideas mientras pensás en ellas
Que si hubiera alguna demora en esa comunicación
entre pensar acerca de algo, verlo y contruir sobre eso
Entonces, existe este mundo entero de ideas, en donde ...
en donde nunca van a poder nacer...
Estas son ideas en las que no podemos pensar...
Las ideas son muy importenes para mi.
Y la cosa acerca de las ideas, es que las ideas comienzan siendo pequeñas.
Las ideas surgen, pequeñas, débiles y frágiles.
Para que las ideas se puedan desarroollar y madurar,
las ideas necesitan un entorno
donde el inventor puede nutrirlas.
Tomar algún tipo de cuidado, alimentárlas, darles formas para que puedan crecer.
Y para mí, ese es el fundamento completo del principio de conexión inmediata.
Y porque las ideas son valiosas para mí,
cuando veo este principio violado,
cuando veo que las ideas se paralizan porque sus inventores no pudieron ver qué estában haciendo
Siento que eso está mal.
Y no "mal" en el sentido de no respetar
alguna guia de estílo o ir en contra buena práctica, sino
"mal" en un sentido mas profundo.
And I'll come back to this, but I want to show you another example of following this principle.
So, in this code here, there is no state
There is no time, there is no interactivity.
And I was thinking about how we would handle those aspects of coding
in a way that's inline with this principle that I have,
that creators need an immediate connection.
So, what I have here, is a little platform game.
Here is my little guy, he can run around, he can jump,
he can die [chuckles].
And the code for him is over here.
So this code makes him run around,
this makes him jump,
this makes him collide with things...
and down here, I've got some code for this little turtle.
And this turtle is not doing much right now
because I haven't finished writing this code,
so, I'm just going to do that right now.
So on each tick, x position plus equals his direction
times the time interval one sixtieth of a second
times some speed,
which, um, I dunno? Could be fast, could be slow
if it's negative, he walks backwards. [chuckles]
And these are all ideas, I can use for other enemies
but I think turtles are supposed to be slow,
so let's set a good speed for a turtle
And then up here, I've got some code that says:
"When my guy, collides with the turtle, he gets some Y velocity".
So it bounces into the air and the turtle gets stopped.
So that looks like that.
And the the turtle gets up after a bit.
The problem is, I don't want the player to be able to get up there yet.
I want the player to bounce up the turtle,
and go through this little passageway down there.
It'll have to go around and solve puzzles and whatnot,
to come back and get the star.
So, the turtle is too bouncy right now.
Now of course I could just turn that down in the code,
and now I can try it
but, but now it's not bouncy enough.
So while it's nice that I can adjust the code while it's running,
without having to stop and recompile and find that place again
I can't immediately see what I need to see,
which is whether or not I make that jump.
So here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to bounce off the turtle,
and pause the game.
So I pause the game, and now there's a slider up here,
which lets me rewind through time.
And now, I could rewind to back before I made the jump,
and change the code, make it less bouncy
and now when I move it forward,
it's going to simulate it, using the same input controls,
the same keyboard commands as before,
but the new code.
[applause]
This is not good enough. [laughter]
I need to be able to see the changes immediately.
I need to be able to see immediately
whether or not my bounciness is correct.
None of this stuff.
And if you have a process in time,
and you want to see changes immediately,
you have to map time to space.
So here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to bounce off my turtle, pause the game,
and now hit this button here,
which shows my guys trail.
So now I can see where he's been.
And now when I rewind,
this trail in front of him, is where he is going to be.
This is his future.
And when I change the code, I change his future. [gasps]
So I can find exactly the value I need,
so when I hit play, he slips right in there.
[applause]
So, creators need to be able to see what they're doing.
If you're designing something embedded in time
you need to be able to control time.
You need to be able to see across time,
otherwise you're designing blind.
As I was playing with this, I noticed it's fun to play with gravity.
So I can make gravity a little negative and he starts to float up in the air. [laughter]
And I can kind of play with that and try to get him to stay there.
And you could probably make an entire game around just the mechanic here - gravity manipulation.
In fact, I bet I could fiddle with any part of this code and come up with an idea for a game.
Even if I just comment out the first statement in the code,
now my guy can't move left - he can only move right.
Which sounds kinda silly, but
Terry Cavanagh actually made a beautiful game
around that concept called "Don't Look Back".
Terry Cavanagh, he made another really wonderful game
which you might have seen, called "V", spelled as the letter v six times.
And, the way that game works, is that you can't jump.
Instead, you can only flip upside down,
and you fall up instead of falling down.
So it kinda works like this.
You can walk on the ceiling or you can walk around on the ground.
And so you have these levels, which kind of look like this
And you kind of walk around and you have to learn how to navigate turning like this
And so if you have like, something like that, you won't be able to jump over
You'll have to like flip over and flip over
And he got an amazing amount of game play out of this concept
So again, being able to try ideas as you think of them.
This example, and the last one with the tree,
these are both very visual programs;
we're able to see our changes just by seeing how the picture changes.
So I was thinking about, how we could do more abstract coding
that's more in line with this principle.
How can we write a generic algorithm in such a way that we can see what we're doing.
So as an example, let's take a look at binary search.
Super quick refresher on how binary search works:
you have an array of values that are in order,
and you have a key, which is the value you're trying to locate within the array.
And you keep track of two variables, which are the lower and upper bounds
of where you think that value could possibly be;
right now, it could be anywhere.
And you look right in the middle of that range -
if what you find is too small, then the key has to be after that.
Look in the middle of the range,
if what you find is too big, the key has to be before that.
And you kind of keep subdividing array into intervals
You narrow in on value you're looking for
And in code, binary search looks like this
And from my perspective, you can't see anything in here
Can't see anything. I see the word array, but I don't actually see an array
And so in order to write code like this, you have to imagine an array in your head
And you essentially have to play computer.
You have to simulate in your head what each line of code would do on a computer
And people that we consider the skilled software engineers
are just those people that are really good at playing computer
But for writing our code on a computer
why are we simulating what a computer would do in our head ?
What isn't the computer just do it and show us ?
So. Let's write binary search.
function binarySearch, takes a key and an array.
And then over here on this side, it's saying
"Ok, it takes a key and an array, such as what?
Give me an example; I need something to work with here."
So, for instance, my array might be 'a', 'b', 'c', 'd', 'e', 'f'.
And let's say for instance we're looking for the 'd'.
So now let's start coding.
The lower bound starts out as zero.
Over here it says 'low = 0', nothing amazing there.
Upper bound starts out at the end of the array, so 'high = array.length - 1'.
And over here, it says 'high = 5'.
So I have my abstract formula in the code.
Over here, it's giving me the concrete value
corresponding to these example arguments.
So I don't have to maintain this picture in my head;
it's just showing it to me.
So now I need the index in the middle of the array,
so I'm going to take the average of those two.
'mid =(low + high)/2', and...well that's obviously not right.
2.5 is not a valid array index. So I guess I need to round this off.
So I'm going to add the floor function and it rounded it down to 2.
And I caught that bug literally the second I typed it, instead of writing an entire function and twenty unit tests.
So now I get the value out of the array...
and then I need to subdivide my range,
which, so this if statement which I'll just paste in here.
So in this case, the value I found is less than the key,
so it's taking this first branch of the if statement.
This is adjusting the lower bound.
Of course if the key was smaller, then
it would take this branch of the if statement and adjust the upper bound.
Or, if the key was 'c', then
we would've just happened to find it on the first shot,  and we'd return the index.
So this is the first iteration of this algorithm.
And now what we need to do, is loop.
We've subdivided the array, we need to keep subdividing
until we narrow in on what we're looking for.
So, we need to loop; I will just loop.
while 1, do all this.
And now what we have are three columns
corresponding to three iterations of this loop.
So this first column here is exactly what you saw before:
low and high span the entire array, we found a 'c', it was too low,
so we adjusted our lower bound, and loop up to here.
Second iteration, bounds are tighter; we found an 'e'.
We adjust the upper bound.
Third iteration, loop up to here; low and high are the same.
We've narrowed it down to a single candidate -
it's indeed the key we're looking for,
and we returned this index.
So there's nothing hidden here;
you see exactly what the algorithm is doing at every point.
And I can go up to here and try different keys,
so I can see how the algorithm behaves for these different input arguments.
And by looking across this data,
I can develop an intuition for how this algorithm works.
So I'm trying different keys here, and say I try looking for a 'g'.
And this looks a little different. It's not actually returning.
And the reason for this is, I'm looking for a key which is not actually in the array.
And the only way of breaking out of this loop, is by finding the key.
So it's kinda stuck here looping forever.
So we can take a look at this and see what went wrong,
where's the algorithm going off the rails.
These first few iterations look fine,
but this iteration looks weird,
because low is greater than high.
Our range is completely collapsed.
So if we get to this point, then we know the key can't be found.
So I see this faulty condition, and I say, "Oh, that's not right; low has to be less than or equal to high."
Okay, well, I'll just put that over as the condition for my while statement.
'low <= high', and then that would break out of the loop,
and I would return some signal to say that it couldn't be found
So here we have 3 iterations 'for loop', couldn't be found
We return the 'not valid' value
So that's what it might be like to write an algorithm without a blindfold on.
[applause]
So I've got this principle, again,
that creators need to be able to see what they doing.
They need this immediate connection with that they're making.
And I've tried to show this principle through three coding examples,
but that's just because this is a software engineering conference,
I thought I was supposed to talk about programming.
But to me, this principle has nothing to do with programming in particular.
It has to do with any type of creation.
So I'd like to show you a couple more demos,
just to show you the breadth of what I have in mind here.
So, to begin with, let's take a look at a different branch of engineering.
So here I have an electronic circuit that I drew.
I'm not quite done drawing it, so let me finish it up there.
Here we'll put 2. And now we have a working circuit.
I mean I assume it's a working circuit. I don't actually see anything working here.
So this is exactly the same as writing code, that we work in a static representation.
But what we actually care about is the data.
The values of the variables, so we can't see that here.
Now in a circuit, the variables are the voltages on these different wires.
So each of these wires has a voltage that's changing over time,
and we have to be able to see that.
Now, if I was building this circuit on a lab bench, building it physically,
I could at least take an oscilloscope and kinda poke around and see
what's going on in the different wires,
what's going on here, or here.
So at the very least, I should be able to do that.
So what I have here, is a plot of the voltage of this wire over time.
You can see it's high, it's low. High.. Low...
So this is clearly oscillating
If I built it physically, also I would be able to see this circuit doing something.
So, in this case I've got these two LEDs up here
These are LEDs, the little lights, presumably there for a reason
I can hit Play and watch it simulate out in real-time
So now you can see what this circuit is doing [applause]
In order to design a circuit like this,
you have to understand the voltage on every wire.
You have to understand how all the voltages are changing throughout the entire circuit.
And just like coding,
either the environment shows that to you, or you simulate it in your head.
And I have better things to do with my head, than simulating what electrons are doing.
So what I'm gonna do, I'm gonna spread it out a bit.
So same circuit, just spread out a little bit,
and I'm going to add the voltage at every node.
So now you can see every voltage throughout the circuit.
And I can even hit Play and watch it all kind of simulate out in real-time.
Although, what I prefer to do is
just move my mouse over it,
and I can kind of look in areas that are interesting to me and see what the values are.
I can compare any two nodes.
So if you look at say the node over here,
while I mouse over this one,
you see the shadow of the one I'm mousing over is overlaid on that.
The shadow of the one I'm mousing over is actually overlaid on all of them.
And so I can compare any two nodes
just by mousing over one of them and looking at the other one.
And again, I can immediately see results of my changes.
So I've got this 70k resistor here.
I want to change its value, I just click and drag it,
and now I see the waveforms changing immediately.
And you'll notice that when I click and drag,
it leaves behind the shadow of the waveform before I started dragging,
so I can compare. I can immediately see the results of my changes.
Two golden rules of information design: show the data, show comparisons.
That's all I'm doing here.
But even this isn't quite good enough.
What we're seeing here are the voltages,
but in electronics there are actually two data types. There is voltage and there is current.
And what we're not seeing is the current,
flowing through each of these components.
And in order to design a circuit, you need to understand both the voltage and the current.
You need to understand the interplay between the two.
That's what analog design is.
So what I'm gonna do is spread these out a little bit more.
And now I'm gonna replace each of these components
with a plot of the current going through it over time.
So each of these blue boxes represents a component.
And you can see which component it is,
because it has a little badge in the corner, a little icon,
but now you can see everything that's going on in the circuit.
You can see how the current changes, you can see how the current and the voltage changes.
There's nothing hidden, there's nothing to simulate in your head.
So what we have here is
a different way of representing the circuit.
Just in general, you could draw any circuit with these blocks
but instead of being made out of little squiggly symbols,
it's made out of data.
And I think it's important to ask:
Why do we have these squiggly symbols in the first place? Why do they exist?
They exist because they're easy to draw with pencil on paper.
This is not paper.
So when you have a new medium, you have to rethink these things.
You have to think how can this new medium allow us to have a more immediate connection
to what we're making. How can this new medium allow us to work in such a way
that we can see what we're doing.
And it's really the same situation with programming.
Our current conception of what a computer program is 
a list of textual definitions that you hand to a compiler.
That's derived straight from Fortran and ALGOL in the late '50's.
Those languages were designed for punchcards.
See, you'd type your program on a stack of cards,
and hand them to the computer operator, (it's the guy in the bottom picture),
and you would come back later.
So there was no such thing as interactivity back then.
And that assumption is baked into our current notions of what programming is.
C was designed for telepipes.
That's Ken Tompson and Dennis Richie up there.
Richie made C.
And there are no video displays in this picture.
Ritchie is basically typing on a fancy typewriter that types back to him.
Any time you use a console or a terminal window, you're emulating a teletype.
And even today, people still think of a REPL
or an interactive top-level as being interactive programming.
Because that's the best thing you could do on a teletype.
So I have one more demo I want to show because I want to emphasize that
this principle, immediate connection, is not even about engineering,
it's about any type of creation.
So I want to move to a different field entirely.
So let's think about animation.
So I've got this painting here, of a tree and leaf on it
and I want to make a little video with the leaf kinda drifting down the tree.
And the normal way of doing this, in a conventional animation package like Flash,
is through keyframes.
So you basically say where you want the leaf to be at different points in time,
and you hit Play and see what it looks like.
So, I'm gonna say: at frame 20, I'm gonna create a keyframe
and the leaf should be there.
At frame 40, create a keyframe and the leaf should be there,
and I'm just totally guessing here. I can not see the motion.
I can not feel the timing,
I'm just throwing things in time and space.
So I've got this leaf at different points in time,
I'm going to add a tween, which tells Flash to connect the dots.
And then I'm gonna hit Play and see what it looks like.
And it looks ridiculous, it looks like billiard balls bouncing back and forth.
And the thing is I kind of know what I want, right ? It's a leaf.
I want leaf drifting down from a tree.
And I can even perform that with my hand: leaf drifting down from a tree.
But Flash doesn't know how to listen to my hand.
But maybe there's a new medium
that does know something about listening to my hand.
So what I'm gonna show you here is a little app I made
for performing animation.
And we're not really set up for doing a live demo off the iPad
so I'm just gonna show you a video of me making a video.
The way this scene is going to play out is
the leaf is gonna kind of drift down from the tree,
and the scene is gonna pan over and the rabbit is gonna do something.
And two things:
one, this is going to move pretty quickly,
and second, I'll be using both hands at almost all times.
So I've got these different layers, the background, the mid-ground and the foreground.
I'm choosing which layer to move using my left thumb.
I'm gonna move my leaf to its position.
I'm gonna move my bunny off stage and start time rolling.
Now I'm gonna perform the leaf drifting down from the tree.
Run it back, check out how that looked.
The motion looks pretty good but the leaf kinda needs to rock back and forth.
So i'm gonna pull out a rotation controller,
run it back, find where the leaf is about to break off,
and record rotation
And I add a little flip there, because it felt right in the moment, wasn't even planned
Stop, because I want to pan over, so I want to drag whole bunch of layers at once
I grab all layers to build a list, i turn down the sensitivity of the background layers
So the leaf would move slower, for a kind of parallax effect
I only want to move horizontally, so I pull out a horizontal dragger
And check out how it looks...
I don't quite like the parallax, so I adjust a sensitivity a little bit.
Try out again. I like that better
So I get ready to go. I run it back to the beginning
so I can kind of get back into the rhythm of the piece.
Leaf hits, I wait a bit and I start panning
And I don't know how many frames I waited. I don't know how long it was
I went when it felt right.
So I panned over this winter scene and kind of slowed down to a stop.
And then I run it back, because I want to do something with my bunny.
Throw away these tools because I'm done with them.
And wait until I think my bunny should move
and he hops away.
And I have got a few different poses for my bunny. So I pull those out.
And then I find the point when the bunny is about to take off the ground.
Which is right there.
I switch his pose and I kind of toggle between the poses as he hops away.
And then I run it back because I wanna check out how it looked
and I'm just gonna bring that up full screen for you.
This is the piece.
So I made that in 2 minutes, performing with my hands like a musical instrument.
Very immediate connection between me and what I was trying to make.
[applause]
One of the inspirations for this tool
was an animation I tried to make several years ago.
Not that one but it also began with a leaf drifting down from a tree.
And I spent all day in Flash trying to keyframe that leaf.
Couldn't do it.
And so that was the end of that.
I still have my storyboards.
Sometimes I play the music I wrote for the piece.
But the piece itself is locked in my head.
And so I always think about
the millions of pieces that are locked in millions of heads.
And not just animation, and not just art, but
all kinds of ideas.
All kinds of ideas, including critically important ideas,
world changing inventions, life saving scientific discoveries.
These are all ideas that must be grown.
And without an environment in which they can grow,
or their creator can nurture them with this immediate connection,
many of these ideas will not emerge.
Or they'll emerge stunted.
So I have this principle that creators need an immediate connection, and
all of these demos that I just showed you simply came from me looking around,
noticing places where this principle was violated,
and then trying to fix that.
It's really all I did.
I just followed this guiding principle
and it guided me to what I had to do.
But I haven't said much about the most important part of the story, which is Why.
Why I have this principle. Why I do this.
When I see a violation of this principle, I don't think of that as an opportunity.
When I see creators constrained by their tools, their ideas compromised,
I don't say: Oh good, an opportunity to make a product.
An opportunity to start a business.
Or an opportunity to do research or contribute to a field.
I'm not excited by finding a problem to solve.
I'm not in this for the joy of making things.
Ideas are very precious to me.
And when I see ideas dying, it hurts.
I see a tragedy.
To me it feels like a moral wrong, it feels like an injustice.
And if I think there's anything I can do about it,
I feel it's my responsibility to do so.
Not opportunity, but responsibility.
Now this is just my thing. I'm not asking you to believe in this the way I believe I do.
My point here is that these words that I'm using:
Injustice, Responsibility, Moral wrong,
these aren't the words we normally hear in a technical field.
We do hear these words in association with social causes.
So things like
censorship, gender discrimination, environmental destruction.
We all recognize these things as moral wrongs.
Most of us wouldn't witness a civil rights violation and think "Oh good, an opportunity."
I hope not.
Instead, we've been very fortunate to have people throughout history
who recognized these moral wrongs
and saw it as their responsibility to address them.
And so there's this activist lifestyle where
a person dedicates themselves
to fighting for a cause that they believe in.
And the purpose of this talk is to tell you that
this activist lifestyle is not just for social activism.
As a technologist, you can recognize a wrong in the world.
You can have a vision of what a better world could be.
And you can dedicate yourself to fighting for a principle.
Socially activists typically fight by organizing
but you can fight by inventing.
So now I'd like to tell you about a few other people who have lived this way,
starting with Larry Tesler.
Larry has done a lot of wonderful things in his life,
but the work I'm gonna tell you about he did in the mid '70s at Xerox PARC.
And at the time, there really wasn't such a thing as personal computers.
The notion of personal computing was very young and
Larry and colleagues at PARC felt that they had transformative potential,
that personal computing could change how people thought and lived.
And I think all of us in this room would agree that they turned out to be right about that.
But at the time,
software interfaces were designed around modes.
So, in a text editor for instance, you couldn't just type
and have words appear on the screen like on a typewriter.
You would be in command mode.
If you wanted to insert text you'd have to press I to go into insert mode
then Escape back out to command mode or maybe you'd hit A to go into append mode.
Or if you wanted to move text around you'd hit M go to the Move mode
and then you'd have to select and move things around
And Larry would watch people using the computer,
they actually pioneered the concept of software user studies, another thing that he did,
but he would watch people using the software and he found that many people
even after training and weeks of use,
many people would not become comfortable with the computer.
And he believed that it was these modes that were to blame.
That the complexity of modes
was a kind of barrier that many people couldn't cross.
And so this kind of represented a threat
to this dream of what personal computing could be.
So Larry made it his personal mission to eliminate modes from software.
And he formed a principle:
"No person should be trapped in a mode"
His slogan that he would go around saying was
"Don't mode me in" and he had it printed on his t-shirt.
And this principle informed everything that he did.
He thought about it with all the work that he did.
And eventually he came up with a text editor called Gypsy,
which essentially introduced text editing as we know today.
There's an insertion point.
And when you typed, words appeared on the screen.
To select text, he invented modeless selection with click and drag.
So you just click and drag over the text you want to select like using a highlighter,
one of the first uses of drag.
To move text around, he invented these commands that he called
Cut, Copy, Paste
So you select and Cut, later on you Paste in, whenever you're ready
You're never trapped in a mode, you don't have the switching between modes
When you hit the 'W' key on a keyboard, you get 'W' on the screen, always.
And he would watch people using his software
and he found that someone who had never seen a computer before,
which was most people back then, 
could be up and running in like half an hour.
So this was clearly a transformative change
in enabling people to connect with computers.
And his ideas about modelessness
spread to the rest of the desktop interface
which was then being invented at Xeroc PARC at the same time.
And today they're so ingrained in the computing experience that today we kind of take them for granted.
Now I said that Larry made the elimination of modes his personal mission.
That's actually his words, and if you think he's exaggerating,
here's Larry's license plate for the last 30 years. [chuckles]
Nowadays of course Larry has a website, at nomodes.com
and he's on twitter: @nomodes
And so like I said, Larry has done a lot of amazing work in his career
but his self identity is clearly associated with this cause.
And so I'd like to ask
What exactly did Larry do?
Like how could we best describe what Larry did?
A typical biography might say:
Larry Tesler invented Cut Copy Paste.
Which is true, but I think it's really misleading, because
this invention was very different than
say, Thomas Edison inventing the phonograph.
Edison basically just stumbled over the technology for audio recording
and he built it out as a novelly.
And he came up with like a this list of possible applications for his technology, but
he didn't have any cultural intent.
Whereas what Larry did was entirely a reaction
to a particular cultural context.
So another thing that you might hear is that
Larry Tesler solved the problem of modeless text manipulation.
Solved the problem. And obviously that's true,
he worked on the problem for a long time, eventually solved it.
But I think that's misleading too,
because this problem that he solved only existed in his own head.
Nobody else saw this as a problem.
For everybody else modes were just how computers worked.
There wasn't anything wrong with them any more than
we think there's something wrong with having two arms.
It just kind of was a fact of life.
So the first thing that Larry did
was that he recognized a wrong that had been unacknowledged in the culture.
And the thing is, that's how many great social changes began as well.
So a 150 years ago, Elizabeth Cady Stanton had to stand up and say:
"Women should vote."
And everybody else said like "That's crazy, what are you talking about ?"
Today, we recognize gender discrimination as a wrong.
Back then, it was part of society, it was invisible.
She had to recognize it, and she had to fight it.
And to me, that's a much closer model to what Larry did
than the Thomas Edison model of inventing a bunch of random technology so he could patent it.
Now to be clear I'm not making any judgement
about the relative importance or the impact of these two people,
I'm just talking about their motivations and their approach.
Both of them recognized a cultural wrong,
they envisioned a world without that wrong
and they dedicated themselves to fighting for a principle.
She fought by organizing, he fought by inventing.
And many other seminal figures in computing had similar motivations.
So certainly Doug Engelbart.
Doug Engelbart basically invented interactive computing.
The concept of putting information on a screen.
Navigating through it.
Looking at information in different ways.
Pointing at things and manipulating them. He came up with all this at a time when
real-time interaction with a computer was just almost unheard of.
Today he is best known as the inventor of the mouse,
but what he really invented with is this entirely new way of working with knowledge.
His explicit goal from the beginning was
to enable mankind to solve the world's urgent problems.
And his vision,
he had this this vision of what he called knowledge workers
using complex powerful information tools to harness the collective intelligence.
And he only got into computers because he had a hunch that these new things called computer things
could help him realize that vision.
Everything that he did
was almost single-mindedly driven by pursuing this vision.
Here's Alan Kay.
Alan Kay ran the lab at Xerox PARC where we got the desktop interface,
so things like windows and icons, command menus.
He also invented object-oriented programming and lots of other things.
His goal, and I quote,
was to "amplify human reach,
and bring new ways of thinking to a faltering civilization
that desperately needed it."
Isn't that great?
His approach was through children. He believed that
if children became fluent in thinking in the medium of the computer,
meaning if programming was a form of basic literacy like reading and writing,
then they'd become adults with new forms of critical thought,
and new ways of understanding the world.
And we'd have this more enlightened society,
similar to the difference that literacy brought to society.
And everything that he did, everything he invented,
came out of pursuing this vision, this goal with children.
And following principles that he adopted from Piaget and Montessori,
Jerome Bruner, these people who would study how children think
And the figure probably most widely associated with software activism
is Richard Stallman.
Stallman started the GNU project which today makes up a big chunk of any Linux system.
He also started the Free Software Foundation,
wrote GCC, GPL, many, many other things.
His principle is that software must be free, as in freedom,
and he has very precise meaning associated with that statement.
He's always been very clear that
software freedom is a matter of moral right and wrong.
And he has taken a particularly uncompromising approach in his own life to that.
All of these tremendously influential people
dedicated their lives
to fighting for a particular ideal with a very clear sense of right and wrong.
Often really fighting
against an authority or mainstream that did not recognize their wrong as being wrong.
And today, the world is still very far from any of their ideals
and so they still see a world in crisis
and they keep fighting. They're always fighting.
Now I'm not saying you have to live this way.
I'm not saying that you should live this way.
What I'm saying is that you can.
That this lifestyle is an option that is available to you.
And it's not one you're gonna hear about much.
Your career counselor is not going to come back to you and say:
"You should start a personal crusade."
In a social field, they might, but not in technology.
Instead the world will try to make you define yourself by a skill.
That's why you have a major in college.
That's why you have a job title.
You are a software engineer.
And you'll probably specialize to be a database engineer
or a front-end engineer,
and you'll be given front-ends and asked to engineer them.
And that could be worthwhile and valuable,
and if you want to spend your life pursuing excellence and practicing a skill,
you can do that. That is the path of a craftsman.
That is the most common path.
The only other path you really hear about much is the path of the problem solver.
So I see entrepreneurship and academic research as kind of two sides of that coin.
There is the field.
There's the set of problems in that field, or needs in the market.
You go in, you choose one, you work it, you make your contribution there.
Maybe later on, you choose another problem, you work it, you make your contribution there.
Again, that could be worthwhile and valuable and if that's what you want to do,
then you can take that path.
But I don't see Larry Tesler on either of those paths.
I wouldn't say he was contributing to the field of user experience design
because there was no such thing.
He didn't choose some open problem to solve,
he came up with some problem that only existed in his own head,
and no one else even recognized.
And certainly he did not define himself by his craft,
he defined himself by his cause.
By the principle he fought to uphold.
And I'm sure if you look at Wikipedia it will say that
he's a computer scientist or a user experience something,
but to me that's like saying Elizabeth Cady Stanton was a community organizer.
No, Elizabeth Cady Stanton established the principle
of women's suffrage. That's who she was.
That was the identity she chose
and Larry Tesler established the principle of modelessness.
He had a vision, and he brought the world to that vision.
So, you can choose this life.
Or maybe it will end up choosing you.
It might not happen right away.
It can take time to find a principle, because
finding a principle is essentially a form of self-discovery,
that you're trying to figure out what your life is supposed to be about.
What you want to stand for as a person.
Took me like a decade.
Ten years before any real understanding of my principles solidified.
That was my twenties.
When I was young I felt I had to live this way
but I would get little glimmers of what mattered to me
but no big picture. It was really unclear.
This was very distressing for me.
What I had to do was just do a lot of things.
Make many things, make many types of things.
Study many things, experience many many things.
And use all these experiences as ways of analyzing myself.
Taking all these experiences and saying:
"Does this resonate with me?"
Does this repel me? Do I not care?
Building of this corpus of experiences that I felt very strongly about for some reason
and trying to make sense of it. Trying to figure out Why?
What is this secret ingredient that I'm reacting to so strongly ?
Now I think everyone's different.
And all the guys I talked about they have their own origin stories
which you can read about.
I will just say that
confining yourself to practicing a single skill
can make it difficult to get that broad range of experiences, which
seem to be so valuable for this sort of work.
And finally,
if you choose to follow a principle,
a principle can't be just any old thing you believe in.
You'll hear a lot of people say they want to make software easier to use.
Or they want to delight their users.
Or they want to make things simple.
That's a really big one right now. Everyone wants to make things simple.
And those are nice thoughts
and maybe kind of give you a direction to go in
but they're too vague to be directly actionable.
Larry Tesler likes simplicity.
But his principle was this specific nugget of insight:
No person should be trapped in a mode.
And that is a powerful principle
because it gave him a new way of seeing the world.
It divided the world in right and wrong in a fairly objective way.
So, he could look at someone selecting text and ask Is this person in a mode?
Yes or no?
If Yes, he had to do something about that.
And likewise, I believe that creators need powerful tools.
It's a nice thought, but it doesn't really get me anywhere.
My principle is that creators need this immediate connection.
So I can watch you changing a line of code, and I can ask:
"Did you immediately see the effect of that change ?" Yes or no.
If No, I got to do something about that.
And again, all those demos that I showed you
came out of me doing that,
of me following this principle
and letting it lead me to exactly what I needed to do.
So if your guiding principle embodies a specific insight,
it will guide you.
And you will always know if what you're doing is right.
There are many ways of living your life.
That's maybe the most important thing you can realize in your life,
is that every aspect of your life is a choice.
But there are default choices.
You can choose to sleepwalk through your life
and accept that path that's been laid out for you.
You can choose to accept the world as it is.
But you don't have to.
If there is something in the world you feel is a wrong
and you have a vision for what a better world could be,
you can find your guiding principle.
And you can fight for a cause.
So after this talk, I'd like you to take a little time and think about
what matters to you.
What you believe in.
And what you might fight for.
Thank you. [applause]